["Rebecca Newberger Goldstein"]
ريبكا نيوبيرغر غولدستين
["Steven Pinker"]
ستيفن بينكر
["The Long Reach of Reason"]
رحلة المنطق الطويلة
Cabbie: Twenty-two dollars. Steven Pinker: Okay.
سائق الأجرة: إثنان وعشرون دولار. ستيفن بينكر: حسنًا
Rebecca Newberger Goldstein: Reason appears to have fallen on hard times:
ريبكا نيوبيرغر غولدستين: يبدو أن المنطق سقط في اوقات صعيبة
Popular culture plumbs new depths of dumbth
الثقافة العامة تتدنى في أعماق الغباء ( دمبث: نظرية صاغها الن ستيفن)
and political discourse has become a race
والحديث السياسي اصبح سباقًا
to the bottom.
إلى القاع.
We're living in an era of scientific creationism,
نحن نعيش في عهد الإبتكار العلمي
9/11 conspiracy theories, psychic hotlines,
نظريات مؤامرات 9/11, الخطوط الساخنة للدجالين
and a resurgence of religious fundamentalism.
و طفرة الأصولية الدينية.
People who think too well
الأشخاص الذين يفكرون جيدًا
are often accused of elitism,
دائمًا يتم إتهامهم بالتحيز للنخبة
and even in the academy,
وايضًا في الأكاديمية
there are attacks on logocentrism,
هنالك هجمات على اللوغوسينتريزم ( تمركز الشارة الإعلانية نظرية صاغها لادويج كلاغيس)
the crime of letting logic dominate our thinking.
جريمة جعلت المنطق يسيطر على تفكيرنا
SP: But is this necessarily a bad thing?
ستفين: لكن هل يعتبر هذا شيء سيء بالضرورة؟
Perhaps reason is overrated.
لربما كان المنطق مبالغـًا في تقديره.
Many pundits have argued that a good heart
الكثير من النقاد جادلوا أن القلب الطيب
and steadfast moral clarity
والثبات على الأخلاق النقية
are superior to triangulations of overeducated policy wonks,
أسمى من الإستعانة بالخبراء السياسين الأكثر تعلمًا.
like the best and brightest and that dragged us
كالنخبة والأذكياء والذي سحبنا
into the quagmire of Vietnam.
إلى قاع فياتنام.
And wasn't it reason that gave us the means
أو لم يكن المنطق هو الذي اعطانا الوسيلة
to despoil the planet
لسلب الكوكب
and threaten our species with weapons of mass destruction?
وتهديد فصيلتنا بأسلحة الدمار الجماعي
In this way of thinking, it's character and conscience,
بطريقة التفكير هذه الشخصية الجيدة والضمير
not cold-hearted calculation, that will save us.
وليست الحسابات الباردة التي ستنقذنا.
Besides, a human being is not a brain on a stick.
إلى جانب أن العقل الإنساني ليس دماغًا فوق عصى
My fellow psychologists have shown that we're led
نظرائي من العلماء النفسيين أروني انه يتم تسيرنا
by our bodies and our emotions
من خلال أجسادنا وعواطفنا
and use our puny powers of reason
ونستخدم قدراتنا الضئيلة على المنطق لنبرهن
merely to rationalize our gut feelings after the fact.
ونبرر فقط أحاسيسنا الداخلية من بعد الحقيقة.
RNG: How could a reasoned argument logically entail
ريبكا: كيف يمكن لحجة منطقية أن يترتب عليها
the ineffectiveness of reasoned arguments?
حجج منطقية غير فعالة؟
Look, you're trying to persuade us of reason's impotence.
أنظر أنتم تحاولون إقناعنا بعجز المنطق على التكاثر
You're not threatening us or bribing us,
أنتم لاترشوننا او تهددونا
suggesting that we resolve the issue
مقترحين علينا أن نحل القضية
with a show of hands or a beauty contest.
برفع الأيادي او مسابقة للجمال.
By the very act of trying to reason us into your position,
بكل محاولة لإقناعنا للإنضمام لموقفكم
you're conceding reason's potency.
أنتم تتخلون عن فحولة المنطق.
Reason isn't up for grabs here. It can't be.
المنطق ليس عرضة للنهش هاهنا ولا يمكن أن يكون
You show up for that debate
أنتم حضرتم لهذه المناظرة
and you've already lost it.
و خَسِرتُموها
SP: But can reason lead us in directions
ستيف: لكن هل بإمكان المنطق أن يقودنا إلى وجهات
that are good or decent or moral?
جيدة أو محترمة أو أخلاقية؟
After all, you pointed out that reason
بعد كل شيء أنتِ أشرتي إلى أن المنطق
is just a means to an end,
وسيلة للغاية
and the end depends on the reasoner's passions.
والغاية تعتمد على شغف المفكر
Reason can lay out a road map to peace and harmony
بإمكان المنطق أن يرسم خارطة للسلام والتناغم
if the reasoner wants peace and harmony,
إذا أراد المفكر السلام والتناغم
but it can also lay out a road map to conflict and strife
لكن بإمكانه أيضًا أن يرسم خارطتًا للنزاع والشقاق
if the reasoner delights in conflict and strife.
إذا كان المفكر يستمتع بالنزاع والشقاق
Can reason force the reasoner to want
هل بإمكان المنطق أن يجبر المفكر على أن يريد
less cruelty and waste?
أقل وحشية وخراب؟
RNG: All on its own, the answer is no,
ريبكا: كذلك من تلقاء نفسه بالتأكيد الجواب لا،
but it doesn't take much to switch it to yes.
لكن تغيّر الإجابة لنعم لا يتطلب الكثير
You need two conditions:
أنتَ تحتاج حالتين:
The first is that reasoners all care
الأولى أن يهتم المفكر كليتًا
about their own well-being.
برفاهيته.
That's one of the passions that has to be present
أن يَحْضُّرَ لديه شغف
in order for reason to go to work,
لكي يٌشَغِل المنطق
and it's obviously present in all of us.
وواضح أننا نمتلكه جميعًا
We all care passionately
نحن جميعًا نهتم بالشَّغف
about our own well-being.
لأجل رفاهيتنا
The second condition is that reasoners
الحالة الثَّانية أنَّهُ يتوجب على المفكرين
are members of a community of reasoners
أن يُكوِنُوا اعضَّاءً من مجموعة من المفكرين
who can affect one another's well-being,
والذين بإمكانهم التأثير على رفاهية بعضهم البعض
can exchange messages,
بإمكانهم تبادل الرسائل
and comprehend each other's reasoning.
و تفهم منطق كل واحد منهم.
And that's certainly true of our gregarious
وبالتأكيد هذا صحيح لفصائلنا
and loquatious species,
الإجتماعية والمكانية
well endowed with the instinct for language.
ذات الموهبة الغريزية اللغوية الجيدة.
SP: Well, that sounds good in theory,
ستيفن: حسنًا نظريًا يبدو هذا جيدًأ
but has it worked that way in practice?
لكن هل هو عملي؟
In particular, can it explain
بالتحديد هل بإمكانهِ أن يشرح لنا
a momentous historical development
التطورات التاريخية بالغة الأهمية
that I spoke about five years ago here at TED?
التي تحدثتُ عنها من قرابةِ خمسة أعوام هاهنا في TED
Namely, we seem to be getting more humane.
بالإسم يبدو أنَّنا أصبحنا اكثر انسانية
Centuries ago, our ancestors would burn cats alive
في القرون الماضية كان بِمقدور سلفنا إحراق القطط حية
as a form of popular entertainment.
كوسيلة شائعة لممتعة
Knights waged constant war on each other
الفرسان شنو حروبًا متواصلة على بعضهم البعض
by trying to kill as many of each other's peasants as possible.
محاولين قتل اكبر قدر ممكن من فلاحي الطرف الأخر
Governments executed people for frivolous reasons,
الحكومات اعدمت الناس لأتفه الأسباب
like stealing a cabbage
مثل سرقة كرنب
or criticizing the royal garden.
او إنتقاد الحديقة الملكية
The executions were designed to be as prolonged
الإعدام تم تصميمه ليكون مطولاً
and as painful as possible, like crucifixion,
و مُؤلمًا بقدر ِ الإمكان وكما الصلب
disembowelment, breaking on the wheel.
وبقرالبطن (إزالة الإحشاء) أو تحطيم العظام على العجلة.
Respectable people kept slaves.
أشخاص محترمين تم الزج بهم في الرق.
For all our flaws, we have abandoned
بالرغم من كل عيوبنا نبذنا
these barbaric practices.
هذه العادات البربرية
RNG: So, do you think it's human nature that's changed?
ريبكا: إذن هل تعتقد أن الطبيعة الإنسانية هي التي تغيرت؟
SP: Not exactly. I think we still harbor instincts
ستيفن: ليس بالظبط مازلنا نُؤوي غرائز
that can erupt in violence,
بإمكانها أن تتفجر إلى عنف
like greed, tribalism, revenge, dominance, sadism.
مثل الجشع والقبلية والإنتقام والهيمنة والسادية.
But we also have instincts that can steer us away,
لكن لدينا أيضًا غرائز بإمكانها ان تقودنا بعيدًا
like self-control, empathy, a sense of fairness,
مثل التحكم بالذات والعطف والإحساس بالعدل
what Abraham Lincoln called
والتي سماها إبراهيم لينكولن
the better angels of our nature.
افضل زوايا الطبيعة الإنسانية
RNG: So if human nature didn't change,
ريبكا: إذن إذا لم تتغير الطبيعة الإنسانية
what invigorated those better angels?
مالذي بإمكانه أن ينعش امالنا في هذه الزوايا الحسنة؟
SP: Well, among other things,
ستيفن: حسناً من بين الأشياء الأخرى
our circle of empathy expanded.
قد توسعت دائرة العطف لدينا
Years ago, our ancestors would feel the pain
في الأعوام الماضية كان بإمكان سلفنا أن يُحِسوا
only of their family and people in their village.
بألام أسرهم او الأشخاص الذين ينتمون لقريتهم.
But with the expansion of literacy and travel,
لكن مع توسع المعرفة والسفر
people started to sympathize
بدأ الناس بالتعاطف
with wider and wider circles,
مع دوائر أوسع
the clan, the tribe, the nation, the race,
العشيرة والقبيلة والوطن والعرق
and perhaps eventually, all of humanity.
ولربما أنتهينا إلى الإنسانية
RNG: Can hard-headed scientists
ريبكا: هل بإمكان العلماء صعبي المراث
really give so much credit to soft-hearted empathy?
إعطاء الكثير من الثقة للعطف الشفوق؟
SP: They can and do.
ستيفن: بإمكانهم وسيفعلون.
Neurophysiologists have found neurons in the brain
علماء فسيولوجية الأعصاب وجدوا أن بعض الأعصاب في الدماغ
that respond to other people's actions
تستجيب إلى أفعال الأشخاص الأخرين
the same way they respond to our own.
بنفس الطريقة التي تستجيب بها إلى أفعالنا
Empathy emerges early in life,
يظهر العطف في مراحل مبكرة من الحياة
perhaps before the age of one.
محتمل قبل سن الواحدة
Books on empathy have become bestsellers,
الكُتب التي تتناول العطف أصبحت تتصدر قائمة أعلى المبيعات
like "The Empathic Civilization"
مثل كتاب " ذا إمباثيك سيفيلايزاشين -حضارة العطف"
and "The Age of Empathy."
و "ذا ااج اوف إمباثي-عصر العطف."
RNG: I'm all for empathy. I mean, who isn't?
ريبكا: أنا كلي للعطف اقصد من ليس كذلك؟
But all on its own, it's a feeble instrument
لكن كل شخص بطريقته, هو أداة واهنة
for making moral progress.
لإحداث تطور أخلاقي.
For one thing, it's innately biased
لشيء واحد أنه ينحاز بالفطرة إلى
toward blood relations, babies
صلات الدم والأطفال
and warm, fuzzy animals.
والحيوانات الدافئة المكسوة بالزغب.
As far as empathy is concerned,
بقدر ما العطف مَعنَّي
ugly outsiders can go to hell.
بإمكان الغرباء القبيحين أن يذهبوا للجحيم.
And even our best attempts to work up sympathy
وحتى أفضل محاولاتنا لإنجاح التعاطف
for those who are unconnected with us
مع هؤلاء غير المرتبطين بنا
fall miserably short, a sad truth about human nature
باءت بالفشل, حقيقة مُحزنة عن الطبيعة الإنسانية
that was pointed out by Adam Smith.
أشار إليها آدم سميث.
Adam Smith: Let us suppose that the great empire
آدم سميث: دعونا نفترض أن إمبراطورية
of China was suddenly swallowed up by an earthquake,
الصين العظيمة إبتلعها زلزال
and let us consider how a man of humanity in Europe
ودعونا نعتبر كيف أن شخصًا ذو إنسانية في أوربا
would react on receiving intelligence
بإمكانه أن يتفاعل مع إدراك
of this dreadful calamity.
هذه المصيبة الفاجعة.
He would, I imagine, first of all express very strongly
بإمكانه أَتَصَور لِلوهلة الأولى أن يُعبِر بقوة
his sorrow for the misfortune of that unhappy people.
عن حُزنهِ لمصيبة ذلك الشعب الحزين.
He would make many melancholy reflections
بإمكانه إصدار إنفعالات حزينة
upon the precariousness of human life,
عن رقة الحياة الإنسانية
and when all these humane sentiments
وعندما يُعَبِرتمامًا
had been once fairly expressed,
عن كل هذه المشاعر الإنسانية
he would pursue his business or his pleasure
سيعود إلى عملهِ أو مُتعتِهِ
with the same ease and tranquility
بنفس السهولة وراحة البال
as if no such accident had happened.
كما لو أنه لم يحدث شيء
If he was to lose his little finger tomorrow,
أما لو كان مقدرًا له أن يفقد بنصره غدًا,
he would not sleep tonight,
لإستحال عليه أن ينام ليلاً
but provided he never saw them,
لكن مع ذكر أنه لم يرهم
he would snore with the most profound security
بإمكانه أن يشخر في أمانٍ عميق
over the ruin of a hundred million of his brethren.
بينما شملَ الدمار مئات الملاين من أخوانه
SP: But if empathy wasn't enough to make us more humane,
ستيفن: لكن إذا لم يكفي العطف لِجعلِنا أكثر إنسانية
what else was there?
مالذي تبقى لنا؟
RNG: Well, you didn't mention what might be
ريبكا: حسنًا أنا لم أذكر ما بإمكانه
one of our most effective better angels: reason.
أن يكون أكثر ملائكتنا الحارسة فعالية: المنطق.
Reason has muscle.
للمنطق عضلات.
It's reason that provides the push to widen
المنطق هو الذي يوفر الدفعة لتوسيع
that circle of empathy.
دائرتنا من العطف.
Every one of the humanitarian developments
كُل التطورات الإنسانية
that you mentioned originated with thinkers
التي ذكرتها نَشئت مِن خِلال مُفكرين
who gave reasons for why some practice
أعطوا أسبابهم للإجابة
was indefensible.
عدم قابلية بعض الممارسات للتغير
They demonstrated that the way people treated
هم برهنوا على أن الطريقة التي يتعامل بها
some particular group of others
الناس مع بعض المجموعات الأخرى
was logically inconsistent
كانت متناقضة منطقيًا
with the way they insisted on being treated themselves.
مع الطريقة التي أصروا على أن يتم معاملتهم بها.
SP: Are you saying that reason
ستيفن: هل تقولين أن بإمكان
can actually change people's minds?
المنطق أن يُغير عُقول الناس؟
Don't people just stick with whatever conviction
ألا يَثبُت الناس مع أي قناعة
serves their interests
تَخدِم مصالحهم
or conforms to the culture that they grew up in?
أو تتوافق مع الثقافة التي ترعرعوا عليها؟
RNG: Here's a fascinating fact about us:
ريبكا: هاهنا حقيقة مذهلة عنا:
Contradictions bother us,
الخلافات تضايقنا
at least when we're forced to confront them,
على الأقل عندما نُجبر على مواجهتها
which is just another way of saying
والتي هي طريقة اخرى لقول
that we are susceptible to reason.
أننا نتأثر بالمنطق
And if you look at the history of moral progress,
وإذا نظرت إلى تاريخ التطور الأخلاقي
you can trace a direct pathway from reasoned arguments
بإمكانك أن تتبع طريقاً مباشرًا من الحوارات المنطقية
to changes in the way that we actually feel.
إلى التغيرات الفعلية في طريقة شعورنا.
Time and again, a thinker would lay out an argument
الوقت مرة اخرة الذي يستغرقة المفكر في مناقشة
as to why some practice was indefensible,
لماذا بعض الممارسات يصعب تغيرها
irrational, inconsistent with values already held.
غير منطقي وغير متزامن مع القيم المُتمسك بها
Their essay would go viral,
هنالك مقال بإمكانه أن ينتشر بصخب
get translated into many languages,
إذا تمت ترجمته إلى عدة لغات
get debated at pubs and coffee houses and salons,
ومناقشته في الحانات والمقاهي وصالونات الحلاقة
and at dinner parties,
وفي حفلات العشاء
and influence leaders, legislators,
و بإمكانه التأثير على القادة والمُشرعيّن
popular opinion.
والرأي العام
Eventually their conclusions get absorbed
حتى يتم أخيرًا إستيعاب إستنتاجاتهم
into the common sense of decency,
إلى لياقة الحس السليم
erasing the tracks of the original argument
ماحين كُل مساراتِ النقاش الأصلي
that had gotten us there.
الذي أوصلنا إلى هذه النقطة.
Few of us today feel any need to put forth
القليل منا اليوم يحسون بالحاجة إلى تقديم
a rigorous philosophical argument
نقاشات فلسفية صارمة
as to why slavery is wrong
لسبب خطأ الرق
or public hangings or beating children.
أو الشنق على مرأى العامة أو ضرب الأطفال.
By now, these things just feel wrong.
الآن هذه الأشياء نشعر بأنها خاطئة
But just those arguments had to be made,
لكن علينا البدء بمناقشتها
and they were, in centuries past.
والتي تمت مناقشتها في قرون ماضية
SP: Are you saying that people needed
ستيفن: هل تقولين أن الناس يحتاجون
a step-by-step argument to grasp
إلى النقاش خطوة بخطوة حتى يتفهموا
why something might be a wee bit wrong
لماذا أن هنالك بعض الخطأ في
with burning heretics at the stake?
حرق الهراطقة على العصى؟
RNG: Oh, they did. Here's the French theologian
ريبكا: اه هم فعلوا. لديك عالم اللاهوت الفرنسي
Sebastian Castellio making the case.
سيباستيان كاستيلو صنع القضية.
Sebastian Castellio: Calvin says that he's certain,
سيباستيان كاستيلو: كالفين قال أنه متأكد
and other sects say that they are.
والطوائف الأخرى أيضًا تقول ذلك.
Who shall be judge?
من عليه أن يكون الحكم
If the matter is certain, to whom is it so? To Calvin?
إذا كان الأمر حتميًا إذن يفوض لمن؟ إلى كالفين؟
But then, why does he write so many books about manifest truth?
لكن لماذا يكتب العديد من الكتب عن الحقيقة الجلية؟
In view of the uncertainty, we must define heretics
من وجهة الشك علينا أن نعرف الهراطقة
simply as one with whom we disagree.
ببساطة كأي شخص ل انتفق معه
And if then we are going to kill heretics,
وعندها إذن سنقتل الهراطقة
the logical outcome will be a war of extermination,
إذن النتيجة المنطقية ستكون حربًا إبادية
since each is sure of himself.
حيث أن كل طرفٍ واثِقٌ مِنْ نفسه
SP: Or with hideous punishments
ستيفن: أو عن طريق طرق تعذيب بشعة
like breaking on the wheel?
مثل تكسير العظام على الدولاب؟
RNG: The prohibition in our constitution
ريبكا: المنع في عرفنا
of cruel and unusual punishments
الوحشي و العقوبات الغير عادية
was a response to a pamphlet circulated in 1764
كانت الرد على منشورات انتشرت في 1764
by the Italian jurist Cesare Beccaria.
من قبل الفقية الإيطالي تشيزاريا بيكاريا
Cesare Beccaria: As punishments become more cruel,
تشيزاريا بيكاريا: لأجل أن تصبح العقوبات اكثر وحشية
the minds of men, which like fluids
عقول الناس والتي هي مثل السوائل
always adjust to the level of the objects
دائمًا تتكيف مع إرتفاع الأشياء
that surround them, become hardened,
المحيطة بهم وتصبح صلبة
and after a hundred years of cruel punishments,
وبعد مئة عام من العقوبات الوحشية
breaking on the wheel causes no more fear
التكسير على الدولاب لم يصبح مصدرًا للخوف
than imprisonment previously did.
مقارنة بالسجن كما كان سابقًا.
For a punishment to achieve its objective,
لأجل أن يُحقق العقاب هدفه
it is only necessary that the harm that it inflicts
على الأذى الذي يتم تطبيقة
outweighs the benefit that derives from the crime,
أن يتخطى المصلحة المستقاة من الجريمة.
and into this calculation ought to be factored
وبهذه الحسبة ينبغي أن تنتج
the certainty of punishment
حتمية العقاب
and the loss of the good
و خسارة الفائدة
that the commission of the crime will produce.
التي سينتجها إرتكاب الجريمة
Everything beyond this is superfluous,
كل شيء بعد ذلك غير ضروري
and therefore tyrannical.
ولأجل ذلك تعسفي
SP: But surely antiwar movements depended
ستيفن: لكن بكل تأكيد الحركات المضادة للحرب تعتمد
on mass demonstrations
على التطبيق الجماعي
and catchy tunes by folk singers
والألحان الجاذبة التي يغنيها معشر المغنين
and wrenching photographs of the human costs of war.
والصور الموجعة التي تعكس التكاليف البشرية للحرب.
RNG: No doubt, but modern anti-war movements
ريبكا: لاشك لكن الحركات المضادة للحرب الجديدة
reach back to a long chain of thinkers
تتصل بسلسلة طويلة من المفكرين
who had argued as to why we ought to mobilize
الذي ناقشوا لماذا ينبقي علينا تحريك
our emotions against war,
العواطف تجاه الحرب,
such as the father of modernity, Erasmus.
مثل أب الحداثة إراسموس
Erasmus: The advantages derived from peace
إراسموس: الفوائد المستقاة من السلام
diffuse themselves far and wide,
تصهر نفسها طولاً وعرضًا
and reach great numbers,
وتصل إلى أعداد غفيرة
while in war, if anything turns out happily,
بينما في الحرب إذا أنتهى أي شيء بسعادة
the advantage redounds only to a few,
فإن المنفعة تشمل القليلين فقط.
and those unworthy of reaping it.
وهم لايستحقون حصادها.
One man's safety is owing to the destruction of another.
سلامة شخص واحد هي سبب لدمار شخص اخر.
One man's prize is derived from the plunder of another.
جائزة شخص مستقاة من سرقة اخر.
The cause of rejoicings made by one side
البهجة التي يصنعها
is to the other a cause of mourning.
طرف هي سبب حداد شخص اخر.
Whatever is unfortunate in war,
أي شيء مؤسف في الحرب
is severely so indeed,
هو قاسي بالتأكيد.
and whatever, on the contrary,
وأي نقيض لذلك
is called good fortune,
يسمى حظ جيد
is a savage and a cruel good fortune,
هي ثروة وحشية وهمجية.
an ungenerous happiness deriving its existence from another's woe.
وسعادة ليست سخية ناشئة من الويل للطرف الاخر
SP: But everyone knows that the movement
ستيفن: لكن كُل شخص يعرف أن حركة
to abolish slavery depended on faith and emotion.
إلغاء العبودية إعتمدت على الإيمان والعواطف.
It was a movement spearheaded by the Quakers,
هي حركة كان رأس حربتها الكويكرس (طائفة بروستانتية)
and it only became popular when Harriet Beecher Stowe's novel
وأصبحت مشهورة عندما تصدرت رواية هاريت بيتشر ستويز
"Uncle Tom's Cabin" became a bestseller.
( انكل توم كابين-كوخ العم توم) أفضل المبيعات.
RNG: But the ball got rolling a century before.
ريبكا: لكن الكرة جرت لقرون قبل
John Locke bucked the tide of millennia
أن يخالف جون لوك تيار آلاف السنين
that had regarded the practice as perfectly natural.
التي إعتَبرَت المُمَارسة طبيعية جدًا.
He argued that it was inconsistent
هو جادل أنها تناقضت
with the principles of rational government.
مع مبادئ الحكومة العقلانية.
John Locke: Freedom of men under government
جون لوك: حرية الناس تحت الحكومة
is to have a standing rule to live by
هي إتخاذ قاعدة يتعايش
common to everyone of that society
من خلالها الجميع في ذلك المجتمع
and made by the legislative power erected in it,
تصنعها السلطة التشريعية التي نُصِبَتْ لها
a liberty to follow my own will in all things
الحرية في أن أتبِع حريتي الشخصية في كل الأشياء
where that rule prescribes not,
حيث تُلزِم القاعدة بعدم الإتباع
not to be subject to the inconstant,
وعدم الخضوع للخلاف و الشك و
uncertain, unknown, arbitrary will of another man,
اللبس و المجهول الذي يأتي مع الإرادة التعسفية لشخص اخر
as freedom of nature is to be under no other restraint
كما أن على الحرية الطبيعة أن لاتخضع لأية قيود
but the law of nature.
إلا القوانين الطبيعية.
SP: Those words sound familiar.
ستيفن: هذه الكلمات تبدو مألوفة.
Where have I read them before? Ah, yes.
أين قرأتها؟ اه نعم.
Mary Astell: If absolute sovereignty be not necessary
ماري استل: إذا كانت الوحشية المطلقة غير مهمة
in a state, how comes it to be so in a family?
في الولاية كيف يتأتى لها في العائلة؟
Or if in a family, why not in a state?
أو إذا كانت العائلة, إذن لماذا ليست الولاية؟
Since no reason can be alleged for the one
حيث أنه لايمكن زعم سبب ليس بإستطاعته
that will not hold more strongly for the other,
أن يَثبُت بقوة أمام سبب أخر
if all men are born free,
إذا ولد كل الرجال احرارًا
how is it that all women are born slaves,
كيف ولدت كل النساء رقيق
as they must be if being subjected
كما أنه يجب إخضاعهن
to the inconstant, uncertain,
للتناقض والغموض
unknown, arbitrary will of men
والمجهول من إرادة الرجال
be the perfect condition of slavery?
والتي تكون أفضل حالات العبودية؟
RNG: That sort of co-option
ريبكا: هذا النوع من الخيار المشترك
is all in the job description of reason.
يتضمنه الوصف الوظيفي للمنطق.
One movement for the expansion of rights
حركة واحدة لأجل توسيع الحقوق
inspires another because the logic is the same,
تُلهم الأخرى لأن منطقها واحد
and once that's hammered home,
و عندها يصبح تكرار الفكرة
it becomes increasingly uncomfortable
غير مُلائم ومتزايد
to ignore the inconsistency.
بحيث يصعب تجاهل الخلاف
In the 1960s, the Civil Rights Movement
في 1960 حركة الحقوق المدنية
inspired the movements for women's rights,
ألهمت العديد من حركات حقوق المرأة
children's rights, gay rights and even animal rights.
وحقوق الطفل وحقوق المثلين وأيضًا حقوق الحيوانات.
But fully two centuries before,
لكن خلال قرنين من الزمان
the Enlightenment thinker Jeremy Bentham
المفكر التنويري جيرمي بينتهام
had exposed the indefensibility
تعرض لما لايمكن تغيره
of customary practices such as
من الممارسات المتعارف عليها مثل
the cruelty to animals.
الوحشية تجاه الحيوانات
Jeremy Bentham: The question is not, can they reason,
جيرمي بينتهام: السؤال ليس مقدرتهم على التفكير
nor can they talk, but can they suffer?
ولا الكلام لكن هل بمقدورهم التألم؟
RNG: And the persecution of homosexuals.
ريبكا: كذلك إضطهاد المثليّن.
JB: As to any primary mischief,
بيتنهام: كما أن أي أذى أولي
it's evident that it produces no pain in anyone.
يبرهن أنه لا يُحدِث ألم لأي شخص
On the contrary, it produces pleasure.
من الناحية الأخرى هو يؤدي للمتعة.
The partners are both willing.
الشريكان كلاهما راغبان.
If either of them be unwilling,
إذا لم يرغب إحداهما
the act is an offense,
لأُعتبرت جنحة
totally different in its nature of effects.
تختلف تمامًا في طبيعة تأثيرها
It's a personal injury. It's a kind of rape.
هي إصابة شخصية ونوع من الإغتصاب.
As to the any danger exclusive of pain,
كما لو أن أي خطر يقتصر على الألم
the danger, if any, much consist
الخطر إذا تواجد يتوقف بصورة كبيرة
in the tendency of the example.
على غاية المثل؟
But what is the tendency of this example?
لكن ماهي غاية المثل؟
To dispose others to engage in the same practices.
هي صرف الأخرين عن تعاطي الممارسات المماثلة
But this practice produces not pain of any kind
لكن هذه الممارسات لاتولد اي نوع من الألم
to anyone.
لأي شخص.
SP: Still, in every case, it took at least a century
ستيفن: مع ذلك كل حالة أخذت على الأقل قرنًا
for the arguments of these great thinkers
لنقاشات هؤلاء المفكرين العظماء
to trickle down and infiltrate the population as a whole.
حتى تناسب وتتخلل المجتمع ككل.
It kind of makes you wonder about our own time.
هي نوع الما تجعلك تتعجب لزماننا
Are there practices that we engage in
هل هنالك ممارسات نقوم بها
where the arguments against them are there for all to see
حيث أن الجدل ضدها واضح للجميع
but nonetheless we persist in them?
لكن بالرغم من ذلك نصر عليها؟
RNG: When our great grandchildren look back at us,
ريبكا: عندما ينظر أحفاد احفادنا إلينا
will they be as appalled by some of our practices
هل سيفزعون بسبب بعض ممارساتنا
as we are by our slave-owning, heretic-burning,
كما لو أننا كنا لهم سلفًا إمتلكوا الرقيق وحرقوا الهراطقة
wife-beating, gay-bashing ancestors?
وضربوا زوجاتهم و قرَّعوا المثليّن؟
SP: I'm sure everyone here could think of an example.
ستيفن: أنا متأكد أن بإمكان البعض هاهنا التفكير في مثال.
RNG: I opt for the mistreatment of animals
ريبكا: أنا أختار الإساءة للحيوانات
in factory farms.
في المزارع الصناعية
SP: The imprisonment of nonviolent drug offenders
ستيفن: سجن مُرتكبي جرائم المخدرات اللاعنيفين
and the toleration of rape in our nation's prisons.
والتساهل مع الإغتصاب في السجون الوطنية.
RNG: Scrimping on donations to life-saving charities
ريبكا: الإحجام عن التبرع لجمعيات الحفاظ على الحياة الخيرية
in the developing world.
في الدول النامية.
SP: The possession of nuclear weapons.
ستيفن: إمتلاك الأسلحة النووية
RNG: The appeal to religion to justify
ريبكا: الإحتكام إلى الدين
the otherwise unjustifiable,
لتبرير مالا يمكن تبريره
such as the ban on contraception.
مثل منع موانع الحمل.
SP: What about religious faith in general?
ستيفن: ماذا عن المعتقدات الدينية بصورة عامة؟
RNG: Eh, I'm not holding my breath.
ريبكا: اه لن أسكت
SP: Still, I have become convinced
ستيفن: أصبحت مقتنعًا
that reason is a better angel
أن المنطق هو ملاك حارس أفضل
that deserves the greatest credit
يستحق منا كل التقدير
for the moral progress our species has enjoyed
لأجل التطور الأخلاقي الذي تستمتع به فصيلتنا
and that holds out the greatest hope
كما أنه يحمل أمل أعظم
for continuing moral progress in the future.
في إستمرارية هذه الأخلاق في المستقبل.
RNG: And if, our friends,
ريبكا: وإذا وَجدَ اصدقائنا
you detect a flaw in this argument,
أي خطأ في هذه المجادلة
just remember you'll be depending on reason
فقط تذكروا أنكم ستعتمدون على المنطق
to point it out.
للإشارة إليه.
Thank you. SP: Thank you.
شكرًا لكم ستيفن: شكرًا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)